José Emilio Pacheco Papers, circa 1940s-2010s: Finding Aid C1619
Manuscripts Division
José Emilio Pacheco Papers
circa 1940s-2010s
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Pacheco, José Emilio
C1619
58 boxes
Consists of the papers (circa 1940s-2010s) of Mexican poet, essayist, novelist and short story writer, José Emilio Pacheco. Materials include notebooks, diaries and journals, writings, correspondence, printed materials, and other items.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of José Emilio Pacheco's handwritten notebooks, in which Pacheco appears to have recorded draft iterations of his writings, miscellaneous notes, and other information related to his creative process; diaries and journals containing handwritten dated entries; writings, such as drafts, excerpts, addenda, and final versions, including poetry, short stories, scripts, screenplays, essays, articles, and translations; a few writings by others; correspondence from various colleagues, publishers, family, and friends, including Octavio Paz, Juan Vicente Melo, Carlos Fuentes, José Miguel Oviedo, Sergio Galindo, Bruno Arcudi, Félix Grande, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, Homero Aridjis, Carlos Monsivaís, Rosario Castellanos, José Bianco, and Vicente Rojo; printed materials, including periodicals, newspaper clippings, articles, publications, and broadsides; and other materials, including photographs, biographical documents, certificates, and materials related to awards given to Pacheco.
Arrangement
As no original order was discernible, materials were arranged in file groups by type of materials. Additionally, a large number of the writings were undated, untitled, unattributed, and in many cases, drafts and fragments mixed together, which were impossible to separate and identify given the disorganized state of the material upon receipt.
Conditions Governing Access
The majority of the collection is open for research. Materials in the "Diaries and Journals" series (boxes B-001261 to B-001268) are restricted for a period of five years, until April 2024, as requested by Cristina Pacheco.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Cristina Pacheco in 2018 (AM 2019-64).
Appraisal
No materials were removed from the collection during 2019 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Pacheco, José Emilio
Biographical / Historical
José Emilio Pacheco was a poet, essayist, novelist and short story writer. He was born in Mexico City on June 30, 1939. Pacheco attended the National Autonomous University of Mexico, where he studied law and literature and worked for literary publications but did not earn a degree. He later taught at various universities in Mexico, United States, Canada, and England, including the University of Maryland at College Park, and the University of Essex, England. Pacheco also worked as director and editor of various journals and cultural supplements. He was given various awards during his lifetime, including the Premio Reina Sofía de Poesía Iberoamericana, and the Premio Miguel de Cervantes, both in 2009. He died in Mexico City on January 26, 2014.
Mexican literature.; Mexican essays.; Mexican poetry.; Poets, Mexican.; Mexico.; Notebooks.; Diaries.; Letters (correspondence).; Manuscripts (documents).; Fuentes, Carlos; Galindo, Sergio; Melo, Juan Vicente, 1932-1996; Oviedo, José Miguel.; Paz, Octavio, 1914-1998
- Notebooks, 1950-2010s; 13 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research. Materials in the "Diaries and Journals" file group (boxes B-001261 to B-001268) are restricted for a period of five years, until 2024, as requested by Cristina Pacheco.
  Scope and Contents
  This file group consists of handwritten notebooks in which Pacheco appears to have recorded draft iterations of his writings, including poems, short stories, ideas, references to other writers, miscellaneous notes, course work, and other information related to his creative process. Some of the notebooks contain dated entries.
  - Notebooks, circa 1950s-1960s; 5 folders (Box B-001248, Folder 1-5)
    Folder 1 contains four notebooks from CUM (Centro Universitario México) titled "Cuaderno de Historial Universal," "Cuaderno de México," "Cuaderno de Moral", respectively, with one notebook being untitled, and primarily contain notes and playscripts, including "La estrella de oro," "El pasado lo guardan las arañas," and "La situación y los sueños".
  - Notebooks, circa 1960s-1970s; 4 folders (Box B-001249, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 1970s; 4 folders (Box B-001250, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 1980s; 4 folders (Box B-001251, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 1980s; 4 folders (Box B-001252, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 1990s; 4 folders (Box B-001253, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 1990s; 5 folders (Box B-001254, Folder 1-5)
  - Notebooks, circa 1990s-2000s; 5 folders (Box B-001255, Folder 1-5)
  - Notebooks, circa 2000s; 4 folders (Box B-001256, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 2000s; 4 folders (Box B-001257, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebooks, circa 2000s-2010s; 5 folders (Box B-001258, Folder 1-5)
  - Notebooks, circa 2010s; undated; 5 folders (Box B-001259, Folder 1-5)
  - Notebooks, undated; 6 folders (Box B-001260, Folder 1-6)
- Diaries and Journals, 1955-2009; 8 boxes
  This file group consists of diaries and journals containing handwritten dated entries documenting Pacheco's daily activities, observations, opinions, and miscellaneous notes and writings. A few of the diaries contain photographs and other items laid-in.
  Materials in this file group are restricted for a period of five years, until 2024, as requested by Cristina Pacheco.
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1955-1960; 5 folders (Box B-001261, Folder 1-5)
    Folder 1 contains a diary (1955) which includes black-and-white photographs laid-in, including portraits of Pacheco and other family members. The photographs are dated between 1956-1960.
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1961-1964; 3 folders (Box B-001262, Folder 1-3)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1965-1969; 3 folders (Box B-001263, Folder 1-3)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1971-1977; 3 folders (Box B-001264, Folder 1-3)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1976-1986; 4 folders (Box B-001265, Folder 1-4)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1986-1996; 3 folders (Box B-001266, Folder 1-3)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 1996-2007; 4 folders (Box B-001267, Folder 1-4)
  - Diaries and journals, circa 2000-2009; 5 folders (Box B-001268, Folder 1-5)
- Writings, 1940-2010s; 22 boxes
  This file group includes drafts, excerpts, addenda, and final versions of various writings by Pacheco, including poetry, short stories, scripts, screenplays, essays, articles, translations, and others. Also included are writings by other authors, including translations of Pacheco's works. A large number of writings were undated, untitled, unattributed, and in many cases, drafts and fragments mixed together, which were impossible to separate and identify given the disorganized state of the material upon receipt.
  - Poetry, 1940-2014; 6 boxes
    Includes handwritten, typewritten, and print out manuscripts of Pacheco's poetry. Some of these writings contain handwritten corrections and annotations. Given the disorganized state of the material upon receipt in the repository, a large number of the poems have been placed in folders labeled as, "Miscellaneous", and it might be the case that some of these writings are not poems.
    - "A mi madre", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 1)
      Contains one of the first poems written by Pacheco, and dedicated to his mother, for which he was awarded a prize in school in Mother's Day.
    - "Album de zoología", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 2)
    - "Antología griega", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 3)
    - "Circo de noche", 1991-1992; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 4)
    - "Ciudad de la memoria", 1986-1989; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 5)
    - "Como la lluvia", circa 2009; 2 folders (Box B-001269, Folder 6-7)
    - "Del último Juan Ramón", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 8)
    - "El mar no tiene dioses", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 9)
    - "El reino de las aves", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 10)
    - "El reposo del fuego", circa 1963-1964; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 11)
    - "El reposo del fuego", 1965; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 12)
    - "El reposo del fuego: a Patricia Llosa y Mario Vargas Llosa", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 13)
    - "El silencio de la luna", 1985-1994; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 14)
    - "El vecino de arriba", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001269, Folder 15)
    - "Elegía del retorno", circa 1984; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 1)
    - "Elogio del jabón", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 2)
    - "En el jardín del haikú", 2000, 2003; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 3)
    - "Epigramas de la antología griega", 2001, 2004; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 4)
    - "Escenas del invierno en Canadá", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 5)
    - "Escrito en una hoja del parque México", 1987 March 31; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 6)
    - "Esta es la noche", 1960; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 7)
    - "Fin de siglo", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 8)
    - "Irás y no volverás", 1973; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 9)
    - "Irás y no volverás", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 10)
    - "Islas a la deriva", 1973; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 11)
    - "Islas a la deriva", 1976 May; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 12)
    - "La arena errante", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 13)
    - "La arena errante", 1999; 1 folder (Box B-001270, Folder 14)
    - "La edad de las tinieblas", 2009; 2 folders (Box B-001271, Folder 1-2)
    - "Límites", 1961; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 3)
    - "Los elementos de la noche", circa 1958-1962; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 4)
    - "Miro la tierra", circa 1983-1986; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 5)
    - "No me preguntes cómo pasa el tiempo", circa 1964-1968; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 6)
    - "Tarde o temprano (Poemas 1958-2000)", circa 2000; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 7)
    - "Tres poemas dementes", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 8)
    - "Tres poemas inéditos", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 9)
    - "Tres poemas sobre casas", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 10)
    - "Viento nocturno", 1957; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 11)
    - "Volver al mar", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001271, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1940s-2014; 6 folders (Box B-001272, Folder 1-6)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1940s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001273, Folder 1-5)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1940s-2014; 4 folders (Box B-001274, Folder 1-4)
  - Short Stories and Novels, 1956-2003; 2 boxes
    - "Ciudad de la memoria", circa 1986-1989; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 1)
    - "Dos ficciones", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 2)
    - "El cerco de Numancia: Miguel de Cervantes", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 3)
    - "El enemigo muerto", circa 1959; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 4)
      Includes translation.
    - "El principio del placer", 1997; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 5)
    - "El principio del placer", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 6)
    - "El príncipe de las tinieblas", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 7)
    - "El torturador", 1961; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 8)
    - "El viento distante", undated; 2 folders (Box B-001275, Folder 9-10)
      Includes the short stories: "El viento distante"; "Virgen de los veranos"; "La cautiva"; "El parque hondo"; "Parque de diversiones"; "Jericó"; "No entederías"; "El castillo en la aguja"; and "La reina"
    - "Eutrapelia", 1961 November; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 11)
    - "La sangre de medusa", 1978; 1 folder (Box B-001275, Folder 12)
    - "La fiesta brava", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 1)
    - "Langerhaus", 1997; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 2)
    - "La niña de Mixcoac", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 3)
    - "La señorita Robles", 2003; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 4)
    - "La oveja reina", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 4a)
    - "Los héroes", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 5)
    - "Los secretos héroes", 1962 October; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 6)
    - "Morirás lejos", 1966; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 7)
    - "Morirás lejos", 1977; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 8)
    - "Morirás lejos", undated; 2 folders (Box B-001276, Folder 9-10)
    - "Muerte en el polvo", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 11)
    - "No perdura", 1962 May; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 12)
    - "Parque de diversiones", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 13)
    - "Paseo en el lago", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 14)
    - "Tres ficciones", 1960 October-December; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 15)
    - "Tríptico del gato", 1956-1957; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 16)
  - Articles and Essays, 1958-2008; 4 boxes
    Includes various articles and essays written by Pacheco, including those from the weekly culture columns, he participated on, "Calendario," "Inventario," "Reloj de Arena," and "El minutero."
    - "Alta traición", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 17)
    - "Calendario", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 18)
    - "Carlos Fuentes en la región más transparente", 2008 August 10; 1 folder (Box B-001276, Folder 19)
    - "Carta de Inglaterra", 1968 February 13; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 1)
    - "Crecimiento del DF: las ciudades y los años", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 2)
    - "Crónica de Huitzilac", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 3)
    - "Crónica del 47", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 4)
    - "Duendes mexicanos", circa 1996; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 5)
    - "El contagio de la culpa", 1968; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 6)
      Introducción al disco de Mario Vargas Llosa en la serie, "Voz Viva de América Latina," México 1968.
    - "El laberinto español", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 7)
    - "El lenguaje de la ciudad", 1961; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 8)
    - "El minutero", circa 1960s; 2 folders (Box B-001277, Folder 9-10)
    - "El modernismo o la moral de la simetría", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 11)
    - "El otro proceso de Kafka (sobre las cartas a Felice), de Elías Canetti", 1976; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 12)
    - "En defensa del usuario: el que recibe las bofetadas", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 13)
    - "Escrito en la oscuridad", 2004; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 14)
    - "Francisco Xavier Clavijero and the Enlightenment in Mexico", 2001 June; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 15)
    - "Gabriel García Márquez: la novela de una novela", 1992 July 30; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 16)
    - "Gustavo Adolfo Becquer", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 17)
    - "Inventario", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001277, Folder 18)
    - "Inventario", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 1)
    - "La batalla del surrealismo (Octavio Paz y la revista Estaciones)", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 2)
    - "La deuda inmensa", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 3)
    - "La literatura mexicana en 1961", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 4)
    - "La picaresca mexicana: elogio de la credencial", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 5)
    - "Libros de nuestros tiempos: Latinoamérica y los Estados Unidos", circa 1975-1976; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 6)
    - "Literatura latinoamericana de 1971", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 7)
    - "López Velarde, Tablada, González Martínez", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 8)
    - "López Velarde: culminación del modernismo mexicano", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 9)
    - "Los demasiados libros", circa 2004 March 5; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 10)
    - "Los hombres de a caballo: el ejército mexicano", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 11)
    - "Los misterios de México: conversación en el café", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 12)
    - "Max Aub y la poesía de las dos orillas", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 13)
    - "Marcel Schwob - Vidas imaginarias - La cruzada de los niños", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 14)
    - "Memorias de un lector mexicano", 1980 June 3; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 15)
    - "Memorias del subdesarrollo: la ineficiencia mexicana", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 16)
    - "No sé quién eres, no sé quién soy: nota sobre persona y biografía", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 17)
    - "Nota sobre la otra vanguardia", 1979; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 18)
    - "La suave patria", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 19)
    - "Nuestra deuda de gratitud con J.L.M.", 1988 January 31; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 20)
    - "Obregón: diez ficciones presidenciales", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 21)
    - "Ovidio en el iPod", 2008 January 1; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 22)
    - "Palabras en reposo, o hay demasiada luz en las tinieblas, Alí Chumacero", 1993 May; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 23)
    - "Panorama de la literatura centroamericana", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 24)
    - "Ramón López Velarde y la posesión por pérdida", 1970; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 25)
    - "Ramón López Velarde: la lumbre inmóvil", 2003; 1 folder (Box B-001278, Folder 26)
    - "Ramón Xirau: Octavio Paz: el sentido de la palabra", 1970; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 1)
    - "Raymundo Ramos Goméz, muerte amurallada", 1958; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 2)
    - "Reloj de Arena", 2000, 2002; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 3)
    - "Rubén Darío en sus dos siglos", 2006 November; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 4)
    - "Tenga para que se entretenga", 1997; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 6)
  - Scripts, 1957 May 3-1990 May 3; 2 boxes
    - "Defecto de fábrica", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 7)
    - "El castillo de la pureza", 1971; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 8)
    - "El castillo de la pureza", 1990 May 3; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 9)
      Adaptación para teatro de: J. Arturo Ramírez Nava.
    - "El castillo de la pureza", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 10)
    - "El desfile salvaje", 1958 December 21; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 11)
    - "El obsceno pájaro de la noche", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001279, Folder 12)
    - "El pasado lo guardan las arañas", 1957 May 3; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 1)
    - "El principio del placer", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 2)
      Adaptación para la escena, Francisco Beverido Duhalt
    - "El santo oficio", circa 1972; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 3)
    - "El santo oficio", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 4)
    - "El santo oficio", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 5)
    - "Foxtrot", 1973-1975; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 6)
    - "La línea de la vida", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 7)
    - "Las horas vacías", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 8)
    - "Los cachorros", 1971 January; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 9)
      Primer tratamiento.
    - "Los cachorros", 1971 February-March; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 10)
    - "Virgen de los veranos", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001280, Folder 11)
  - Translations, 1961-2010s; 2 boxes
    - "Antología griega y haikus", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001281, Folder 1)
    - "Cuatro cuartetos", circa 2010s; 1 folder (Box B-001281, Folder 2)
    - "Cuatro cuartetos", undated; 3 folders (Box B-001281, Folder 3-5)
    - "De profundis", 2001; 1 folder (Box B-001281, Folder 6)
    - "De profundis", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001281, Folder 7)
    - "Diario de David Rubinowicz", 1961; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 1)
    - "Diccionario de ideas", 1962; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 2)
    - "Dos cuentos de Ray Bradbury, inéditos en español", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 3)
    - "Dos poemas de Steven F. White", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 4)
    - "Dos poemas ingleses, Jorge Luis Borges", 2000 January; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 5)
    - "El cantar de los cantares", 2008; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 6)
    - "El libro de las adivinanzas", 2012; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 7)
    - "El circo de Numancia, tragedia de Miguel de Cervantes", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 7a)
    - "La gruta de las palabras", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 7b)
      Treinta poemas de Vladimir Holan.
    - "La estrella humeante: 14 poemas mayas", 2011; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 8)
    - "Poemas de Alastair Reid", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 9)
    - "Poemas de Vladimir Holan", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 9a)
      Versiones de Daniela Grollova y José Emilio Pacheco.
    - "Poemas de Zbigniew Herbert", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 10)
    - "Un tranvía llamado Deseo", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 11)
    - "Victor Hugo", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 13)
  - Other Writings, 1950-2014; 8 boxes
    - "El columnista", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 14)
    - "El desierto viviente", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 15)
      Text written by Pacheco as a student in a biology course.
    - "Fernando Benítez - Dictador - La sombra de Trujillo", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 16)
    - "Huitzilac", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001282, Folder 17)
    - "La Guerra Cristera", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 1)
    - "Los jóvenes macabeos", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 2)
    - "Manuel Gutiérrez Nájera", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 3)
    - "Pepe Batán", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 4)
    - Prólogo: "Rodolfo Walsh desde México", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 5)
    - Prólogo: "Rubén Darío en sus dos siglos", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001283, Folder 6)
      Includes accompanying text.
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 2 folders (Box B-001283, Folder 7-8)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001284, Folder 1-5)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001285, Folder 1-5)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001286, Folder 1-5)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001287, Folder 1-5)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 4 folders (Box B-001288, Folder 1-4)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2014; 5 folders (Box B-001289, Folder 1-5)
  - Writings by others, 1946 May-2008; 1 box
    - "An Ark for the Next Millenium", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 1)
      Poems by José Emilio Pacheco. Translations by Margaret Sayers.
    - "Borges y el civilizado arte de la traducción: una infidelidad creadora y feliz," Rafael Olea Franco, 2001; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 1a)
    - "Ciudad de la memoria de José Emilio Pacheco: hacia la creación de un único poemario," María Rosa Olivera-Williams, 1991; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 2)
    - "De la ansiedad de influencias: Borges en Pacheco," Rafael Olea Franco, 2004 September; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 3)
    - "El mar sigue adelante," Jomi Delgado Azorín, 2008; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 4)
      Para barítono y piano.
    - "El perseguidor," Julio Cortázar, 1956; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 5)
    - "La literatura puesta en juego: (La dialéctica literatura-testimonio en Morirás lejos de José Emilio Pacheco," Raúl Dorra, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 6)
    - "La venganza creadora," Alfonso Reyes, 1946 May; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 7)
    - "Música de animal lluvioso," David Maradiaga, circa 1990s; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 8)
    - "Nicaragua: el enigma de las elecciones," Grabriel Zaid, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 9)